"Risks and Benefits of
Nicotinamide (NAM), a NAD+ Booster"
Ever since nicotinamide (NAM)
was also shown to cure pellagra,
both nicotinic acid, NA, and NAM have been
collectively referred to as niacin or vitamin B3,
though they are
distinct compounds.
For example, NAM is not plagued by
the same kind of hot flash reaction.
(Facial flushing attributed to
niacinamide in some older studies
was likely due to a less purified
form contaminated with residual NA.)
The relative capacity of NA versus
NAM to generate NAD+ is unclear.
Neither has been shown
to boost sirtuin activity,
but both do extend the
lifespan of C. elegans.
I couldn’t find any longevity
trials for NA in rodents;
however, NAM was put to the test
and failed to prolong the lives of mice.
What clinical effects might
we expect in people?
Previously, I explored the proven anti-
aging effects for topical nicotinamide
on the skin and the remarkable ability of
oral nicotinamide to help prevent skin cancer.
I also noted it failed to
prevent type 1 diabetes,
despite promising mouse data,
though it may help preserve
residual function in people
newly diagnosed with
type 1 diabetes,
but apparently not enough
to affect blood sugar control.
What about its use
as a NAD+ booster?
In those with
mitochondrial myopathy,
NA raised muscle NAD+ levels and
improved mitochondrial and muscle function,
but in healthy individuals,
muscle NAD+ levels didn’t budge.
However, the average age of individuals
in the control group was 50.
What about in older adults whose muscle
NAD+ levels might potentially be lower?
Four NAD+ precursors were tested
in older adults averaging in their 70s:
tryptophan, NA, NAM, and NR.
All four failed to improve
muscle strength or function,
failed to affect mitochondrial function,
and failed to even nudge
NAD+ levels in their muscles.
Why not give it a try anyway?
Again, side effects.
Like NA, high-dose NAM can cause
gastrointestinal disturbances
and signs of liver toxicity….
However, NAM may result in more
issues involving methylation.
The first step in breaking down excess
NAM is to transfer a methyl group to it,
forming methylnicotinamide.
Unfortunately,
methylnicotinamide is neurotoxic
and can cross the
blood-brain barrier.
This may explain why NAM can exacerbate
Parkinson’s-like symptoms in rats
and why Parkinson’s patients
have higher levels
of the NAM-methylating
enzyme in their brains.
And the same with Alzheimer's
brains for that matter.
Excess NAM may also deplete
the body’s pool of methyl groups.
If you read the Epigenetics chapter
in my book How Not to Age,
you may remember that DNA methylation is
critical for the regulation of gene expression.
Epigenetic changes caused by
NAM-induced methyl depletion
have been blamed as the reason
why rats fed megadoses of NAM
suffer from fatty livers
and swollen kidneys,
but that was at a human-equivalent dose
far exceeding what people might take.
Is there any evidence that
more modest NAM supplementation
might affect methylation in humans?
Yes, and even with a single
dose as low as 100 mg.
Methylation also plays a key role in
breaking down fight-or-flight hormones
like noradrenaline and neurotransmitters
like serotonin and histamine.
Within hours of a single
100 mg dose of NAM,
blood levels of all three
become elevated,
suggesting their metabolism was impaired
by the shunting of methyl groups
to deal with the excess NAM.
Also noted was a significant
rise in homocysteine,
which is a byproduct of
methylation reactions
and a risk factor for cardiovascular
disease and dementia.
Another potential problem with NAM
is that it’s a sirtuin inhibitor.
Wait, I thought the whole purpose of taking
NAD+ precursors is to boost sirtuin activity.
Sirtuin enzymes use up
NAD+ and spit out NAM.
This allows the body to recycle the NAM
back into NAD+ for further sirtuin use.
But it also means the body can use
NAM as part of a negative feedback loop.
Like a thermostat in the winter
that shuts down the furnace
when there’s too much heat,
the body shuts down NAD+ use by
sirtuins when it detects too much NAM.
NAM pills didn’t exist
when our bodies evolved;
so, in the wake of a
sudden wave of NAM,
the body must think its sirtuins are
churning out too much and dials them back.
Perhaps, this explains why NAM
fails to prolong the lifespans of mice.
When the sirtuin-suppressing effects of
NAM were first reported 20 years ago,
the researchers cautioned that
this could potentially lead to
“deleterious consequences of long-term
nicotinamide therapy in humans.”